Overview and Research Interests

(As of December 17, 2022) I'm a senior researcher in the PROSE team at Microsoft, where I work on developing state-of-the-art program synthesis technologies to make writing and using software easier and more enjoyable. Prior to this, I graduated from MIT with a PhD in Computer Science, advised by Martin Rinard.

Education

Academic Qualifications

2016-2021 PhD in Computer Science

Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA.

2013-2016 Masters in Computer Science

New York University: Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences, NY, NY. GPA: 3.89, MS Research/Thesis Fellowship Award Fall 2015, funding work on A2Q (an order-aware optimizing query compiler for AQuery)

2007-2011 Bachelor of Arts in Economics and Minor in German Studies

University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA. GPA: 3.93, Phi Beta Kappa, Summa Cum Laude, Dean's List (08, 09, 10)

Industry Work Experience

June 2022 to **Senior Researcher** *PROSE Team*, Microsoft, Remote.

date o Working on program synthesis technologies for a variety of developer, data scientist, and

end-user applications. Currently focused on automated program repair using neurosymbolic methods and large language models.

July 2021 to Researcher PROSE Team, Microsoft, Remote. June 2022

Summer 2020 Intern Facebook AI Research, Facebook, Remote (due to COVID-19).

• Worked with the SysML team on a novel tensor compiler, writing C++ for JIT compilation, benchmarking against Halide/TVM

Fall 2018 Part-Time Research Collaborator Big Code Team, Facebook, Remote.

o Applying deep learning to identify and highlight core code functionality

Summer 2018 Intern Software Engineering, Facebook, Boston.

o Applying deep learning to code search Worked with the Big Code team on applications of neural networks to code search

Summer 2015 Intern Data Science. Cloudera. San Francisco.

2011 - 2014 Full-Time Securitized Credit Research Associate Non-Agency Mortgages and US Housing, Morgan Stanley, New York.

Summer 2010 Richard B. Fisher Scholar Fixed Income Generalist Sales and Fixed Income Credit Strategy, Morgan Stanley, New York.

> \$\square\$ 215-900-5308
>
> ■ josepablo@gmail.com www.josecambronero.com • www.github.com/josepablocam

Summer 2009 **Douglas Paul Scholar** *Investment Banking and Alternative Investments*, Morgan Stanley, New York.

Academic Work Experience

Fall and Spring Advanced Undergraduate Research Class *TA*, MIT. 2021

2015 – 2016 Graduate Course in Compiler Construction *Grader*, NYU.

Fall 2014 Graduate Course in Programming Languages Teaching Assistant, NYU.

Publications

- [1] Jose Cambronero, John Feser, Micah Smith, and Samuel Madden. Query optimization for dynamic imputation. *PVLDB*, 10(11):1310–1321, 2017.
- [2] José P. Cambronero, Jiasi Shen, Jürgen Cito, Elena Glassman, and Martin Rinard. Characterizing Developer Use of Automatically Generated Patches. In *VL/HCC (Short Paper)*, 2019.
- [3] José P. Cambronero, Hongyu Li, Seohyun Kim, Koushik Sen, and Satish Chandra. When Deep Learning Met Code Search. In *FSE (Industry Track)*, 2019.
- [4] José P. Cambronero, Thurston H.Y. Dang, Nikos Vasilakis, Jiasi Shen, Jerry Wu, and Martin Rinard. Active Learning for Software Engineering. In *SPLASH Onward!*, 2019.
- [5] José P. Cambronero and Martin Rinard. AL: Autogenerating Supervised Learning Programs. In SPLASH OOPSLA, 2019.
- [6] José P. Cambronero, Jürgen Cito, and Martin Rinard. AMS: Generating AutoML Search Spaces from Weak Specifications. In *ESEC/FSE*, 2020.
- [7] Limor Appelbaum, José P. Cambronero, and et al. Development and Validation of a Pancreatic Cancer Risk Model for the General Population Using Electronic Health Records: An Observational Study. In European Journal of Cancer, 2020.
- [8] Fatjon Zogaj, José Pablo Cambronero, Martin C Rinard, and Jürgen Cito. Doing more with less: characterizing dataset downsampling for automl. *Proceedings of the VLDB Endowment*, 14(11):2059–2072, 2021.
- [9] José P. Cambronero, Micah Smith, Jürgen Cito, and Martin Rinard. Learning Repair Rules for Machine Learning Pipelines from AutoML Search Traces. In *Under submission*, 2020.
- [10] José P. Cambronero, Raul Castro Fernandez, and Martin Rinard. wranglesearch: Mining Data Wrangling Functions from Python Programs. In *Under submission*, 2021.
- [11] Rohan Bavishi, Harshit Joshi, José Cambronero, Anna Fariha, Sumit Gulwani, Vu Le, Ivan Radiček, and Ashish Tiwari. Neurosymbolic repair for low-code formula languages. *Proc. ACM Program. Lang.*, 6(OOPSLA2), oct 2022.
- [12] Harshit Joshi, José Cambronero, Sumit Gulwani, Vu Le, Ivan Radicek, and Gust Verbruggen. Repair is nearly generation: Multilingual program repair with Ilms. arXiv preprint arXiv:2208.11640 (to appear AAAI 2023), 2022.
- [13] José Cambronero, Sumit Gulwani, Vu Le, Daniel Perelman, Arjun Radhakrishna, Clint Simon, and Ashish Tiwari. Flashfill++: Scaling programming by example by cutting to the chase. In *Principles of Programming Languages*. ACM SIGPLAN, ACM, January 2023.
- [14] Bram Wasti, José Pablo Cambronero, Benoit Steiner, Hugh Leather, and Aleksandar Zlateski. Loopstack: a lightweight tensor algebra compiler stack. *arXiv preprint arXiv:2205.00618*, 2022.

Language skills

- o Programming Languages: Proficient in: Python, Java, C, q, R, Scala.
- o Natural Languages: Native fluency in English and Spanish. Working proficiency in German.

Service

o Artifact Evaluation Committee OOPSLA 2020, CAV 2020, PPoPP 2018

Mentoring/Advising

- o Harshit Joshi (Microsoft): research fellow advisor
- o Jialu Zhang (Yale/Microsoft): summer 2022 internship advisor
- o Jennifer McCleary (MIT) MEng Thesis: pancreatic cancer risk modeling (Fall 2019 January 2020)
- o Alex Berg (MIT) Undergraduate research: pancreatic cancer risk modeling (Summer 2020)
- o Thomas Xiong (MIT) MEng Thesis: pancreatic cancer risk modeling (Fall 2020 Spring 2021)
- o Lori Zhang (MIT) Undergraduate research: pancreatic cancer risk modeling (Summer 2020 Spring 2021)